Guide to the Johnson family papers, 1798-1943
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Johnson family papers, 1798-1943
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Johnson family (Ala.)
3.0 Linear Feet Approx. 758 Items
Alabama family whose members were instrumental in founding the Alabama School for the Deaf in Talladega.
The Johnson family's papers chiefly contain letters (1927-1930) from Nellie Hall Johnson (wife of Joseph Henry Johnson Jr.), of Talladega, Alabama, to her son, Seaborn Johnson, while he was a student at Alabama Polytechnic Institute and elsewhere. Other papers represent three generations of the Johnson family in Alabama and Georgia, and include correspondence, some legal and financial papers, student papers from the University of Alabama, and printed material. Of particular interest is the 1861 muster roll of the Alabama Rifles, and items referring to the sale of slaves. Other topics in the family papers include life in Cave Spring, Georgia and the history of Hollins College. Persons represented include Abner Darden, Joseph Henry Johnson Jr., and the Asbury and Darden families.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Johnson family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1978.
Biographical Note
The Johnson family was an Alabama family whose members were instrumental in founding the Alabama School for the Deaf in Talladega. The younger Seaborn's namesake, Seaborn Johnson, was born deaf in 1845; his older brother, Joseph Henry Sr., worked at the Georgia School for the Deaf in Cave Spring, and founded the Alabama School for the Deaf in Talladega in 1858. Seaborn was the first student attending the school, then went on to Gallaudet University. Nellie's husband Joseph Henry was the son of Joseph Henry Sr. and Emily Johnson.
The Johnson family's papers chiefly contain letters (1927-1930) from Nellie Hall Johnson (wife of Joseph Henry Johnson Jr.), of Talladega, Alabama, to her son, Seaborn Johnson, while he was a student at Alabama Polytechnic Institute and elsewhere. Other papers represent three generations of the Johnson family in Alabama and Georgia, and include correspondence, some legal and financial papers, student papers and writings from the University of Alabama, and miscellaneous printed material.
The legal papers contain several early land deeds and plats for Georgia and Alabama. Some of the deeds and bonds were Abner Darden's. Darden was the father-in-law of Joseph Henry Johnson. Other legal records are those of Mary E. Latimer as guardian of the minor heirs of Richard V. Asbury, will of Joseph H. Johnson, undated constitution and by-laws for the formation of the Cave Spring (Ga.) Mechanic's Aid Association or Joint-Stock Company to sell family groceries, and interrogations taken by Abner Darden for a lawsuit in Polk Co., Ga., relative to the financial condition of Woodland Female College. Among the financial records are those of Abner Darden, Richard V. Asbury, Mary E. Latimer, inventories of the sale of personal property of the late William Darden of Taliaferro Co., Georgia, on Nov. 10, 1842, and of the sale on Dec. 22, 1842, of his slaves, which includes prices.
Among the miscellaneous papers are a copy of the original muster roll of the Alabama Rifles (Alabama 1st Infantry Regiment, Company "D") Apr. 3, 1861, of which Joseph H. Johnson was captain, and a commission of Johnson as a representative of the Grand Commandery of Knights Templar of Kentucky to the Grand Commandery of Alabama, May 28, 1870. Printed items include a list of Georgia officials, circa 1857, that shows that the state senators and representatives were either of the Democratic or American Party; a memorial article on Abner Darden by his lifelong friend Alexander H. Stephens, July 30, 1877; and the June 8, 1893, issue of The Messenger of Talladega printed on silk and devoted solely to the life, career, and death of Dr. Joseph H. Johnson.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Asbury family
Confederate States of America. Army. Alabama Infantry Regiment, 1st
Darden, Abner
Darden family
Johnson family (Ala.)
Johnson, Joseph Henry Jr., 1864-1914
Johnson, Nellie Hall
Johnson, Seaborn
Alabama Polytechnic Institute -- Students
Hollins College -- Students
University of Alabama -- Students
College students -- Correspondents
Mothers and sons -- Southern States
Slavery -- Southern States
Universities and colleges -- Alabama
Alabama -- History
Alabama -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Georgia -- History
Cave Spring (Ga.)
Talladega (Ala.)
Description of Collection
- Johnson family papers, 1798-1943, (4 boxes)
  - Accession 1-04-1978
    - Correspondence, 1839-1883 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1884-1926 (Box 2)
  - Unmarked Addition
    - Correspondence, 1883-1943 (Box 1)
    - Legal papers, 1798-1924 (Box 2)
    - Financial papers, 1836-1930 (Box 2)
    - Addresses and writings, 1863-1893 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1861-1929 (Box 2)
      Includes Alabama Rifles muster roll, 1861.
    - Printed material, 1857-1877 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1883-1943 (Box 2)
  - Oversize papers (Opaperfolder 1)